Guide to the Alan H. Kempner Collection of Literary Letters and Manuscripts
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alan H. Kempner Collection of Literary Letters and Manuscripts,
1809-1981.
Kempner, Alan H., 1897-1985, collector.
0.5 linear ft. (36 itemsin 1 box).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078412
Biographical Note
Alan Kempner (Columbia A.B., 1917) was a stockbroker, publishing executive, book collector and philanthropist who donated books, manuscripts and drawings to Columbia University Libraries.
Scope and Content
A collection of letters and manuscripts of English and American authors, including one item from each of the following: Pearl S. Buck, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Thomas De Quincey, Thomas Frognall Dibden, Charles Dickens, William Ewart Gladstone, Edmund Gosse, Hester Thackeray Ritchie Fuller, Rockwell Kent, Charles Kingsley, Edward George Bulwer Lytton, John Masefield, Clinton Scollard, William Wordsworth and Walt Whitman. In addition, there are 8 letters from Samuel Rogers (1763-1855) to Mr. and Mrs. Horace Twiss, photographs of Alan and Margaret Kempner and miscellaneous Kempner items.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence & Manuscripts
Series II: Photpgraphs, Memorabilia and Miscellaneous
Series III: Books
Subjects
Adler, Elmer, 1884-1962.; Blore, Edward, 1787-1879.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Canton, William, 1845-1926.; Coleridge, Samuel Taylor, 1772-1834.; De Quincey, Thomas, 1785-1859.; Dibdin, Thomas Frognall, 1776-1847.; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898.; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928.; Kennedy, Willaim Sloane, 1850-1929.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Kingsley, Charles, 1819-1875.; Lytton, Edward Bulwer Lytton, Baron, 1803-1873.; Masefield, John, 1878-1967.; Ollier, Charles, 1788-1859.; Rogers, Samuel, 1763-1855.; Scollard, Clinton, 1860-1932.; Twiss, Horace, 1787-1849.; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892.; Wordsworth, William, 1770-1850.; Authors, English.; Authors, American.; Catalogs.; Certificates.; Lists.; Loose leaf catalogs.; Manuscripts.; Notes.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Artists.; Novelists.; Poets.; Politicians.; Prime ministers.; Statesmen.; Women authors, American.
Acquisition
1975 M-1975 Literary letters and mss Kempner, Alan H. Gift
01/02/86 M-86-01-02 Literary letters and mss Kempner, Margaret L. Gift
01/02/86 M-86-01-02 4 books Kempner, M.L. Gift
Alternate Formats
Pearl S. Buck letter is on microfilm.
Gift of Alan H. Kempner, 1975; Gift of Margaret L. Kempner, 1986.
- Series I: Correspondence & Manuscripts
  - Buck, Pearl Sydenstricker To Alan H. Kempner, 9 November 1940. (, (Typed letter signed) (Box 1)
  - Coleridge, Samuel Taylor To J. P. Kennard, 13 August 1832, (Manuscript ltter, 3 pages) (Box 1)
    (copy, including signature, not in author’s hand; note on page 4 concerning the original letter, by J. Wright Oxberry, who made the copy)
  - Dibden, Thomas Frognall To Edard Blore, 25 October 1923., (Autograph letter signed, 1 page) (Box 1)
  - Dickens, Charles To "Dear Madam", 13 December 1852., (Authgraph letter signed, 1 page) (Box 1)
    (Fragment, middle of the page cut away)
  - De Quincey, Thomas Confessions of an English Opium Eater., (Autograph manuscript, 2 pages) (Box 1)
    (Numbered "Cc")
  - Fuller, Hester Thackeray Ritchie To Anthony [Philip Martineau Walker], (Autograph letter signed, 4 pages) (Box 1)
  - Gladstone, William. [Irish Church Bill], 21 June 1869, (Autograph manuscript, 1 page) (Box 1)
    (Written on an envelope; note on Lord Gray’s amendment in Gladstone’s hand)
  - Gosse, Edmund To William Canton, 23 March 1894, (Autograph letter signed, 2 pages) (Box 1)
  - Kent, Rockwell To Elmer Adler, 1 July 1937, (Typed letter signed, 1 page) (Box 1)
  - Kingsley, Charles To _____, 23 April 1850, (Autograph letter signed, 2 pages) (Box 1)
  - Lytton, Edward George Bulwer To Charles Olliver, 5 December 1828, (Autograph letter signed, 3 pages) (Box 1)
    (Fregile, broken at the folds)
  - Masefield, John To Mary Dowdall, 6 February 1920, (Autograph letter signed, 2 pages) (Box 1)
  - Rogers, Samuel To Horace Twiss (1787-1849), [no date] and 1809-8 July 1944., (5 Autograph letters signed; 1 autographed letter; 3 autographed notes signed) (Box 1)
  - Scollard, Clinton To Mrs de Lima, 5 July [n.y.], (Autographed letter signed) (Box 1)
  - Whitman, Walt To William Sloane Kennedy, 11 August 1886, (Autographed post-card signed, with initials) (Box 1)
  - Wordsworth, William To "My dear Sir", [no date], (Autograph letter, 1 page) (Box 1)
    (Fragmant of letter, with manuscript note on verso in another hand)
- Series II: Photpgraphs, Memorabilia and Miscellaneous
  - Photographs of Alan H. Kempner, (1 Folder) (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Margaret L. Kempner, (1 Folder) (Box 1)
  - Kempner, Margaret Loeb. 2 letters to her from Michael Sovern and Ernest W. Michel (Box 1)
  - Play Schools Association calligraphic broadside (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous:
    - List of the Alan H. Kempner Library, (60 pages, 2 copies) (Box 1)
    - Prints from the Collection of Alan Kempner. Printed, 3 copies (Box 1)
    - Blank watermarked leaf by Thomar Prado (Box 1)
    - Envelope relating to Samuel Rogers purchase (Box 1)
- Series III: Books
  - Kempner, Alan H. The Lane, (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Kempner, Alan H. Recollection: a Personal Memoir of Alan H. Kempner, (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Michel, Ernest W. Promises To Keep (Box 1)